<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-01-22T00:29:44+01:00</updated><id>https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Welcome to my site! </subtitle><entry><title type="html">श्रीगणेशपञ्चरत्नस्तोत्रम्</title><link href="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/ganesh-pancharatnam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="श्रीगणेशपञ्चरत्नस्तोत्रम्"/><published>2023-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/ganesh%20pancharatnam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/ganesh-pancharatnam/"><![CDATA[<p>In progress; To be improvised further; <br/></p> <div id="ganesh_pancharatnam"> <table border="1" class="tg" style="width: 100%"> <colgroup> <col span="1" style="width: 30%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 34%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 36%"/> </colgroup> <thead> <tr> <th class="tg-c3ow">Sanskrit (देवनागरी)</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">शब्दार्थ (Meaning of words)</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">English Translation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> मुदाकरात्तमोदकं सदाविमुक्तिसाधकं<br/> कलाधरावतंसकं विलासिलोकरक्षकम् । (विलासिलोकरञ्जकम्)<br/> अनायकैकनायकं विनाशितेभदैत्यकं<br/> नताशुभाशुनाशकं नमामि तं विनायकम् ॥ १॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> मुदा - happiness, कर - giving, तम - that, उदकं - sweet drink (Modaka)<br/> सदा - always, विमुक्तिसाधकं - bestower of liberation<br/> कला - art, धर - holding, वतंसकं - wearing as an ornament<br/> विलासि - playful, लोक - world, रक्षकं - protector (Vilasalokaraksakam)<br/> अनाय - without a leader, एक - one, नायकं - leader<br/> विनाशित - destroyed, इभ - elephants, दैत्यकं - demon (Vinashitebha-dait-yakam)<br/> नत - bow, अशुभ - inauspiciousness, अशुनाशकं - destroyer of misfortunes<br/> नमामि - I bow, तं - to that, विनायकं - Lord Vinayaka<br/> (विलासिलोकरञ्जकम् - adorned with the delight of the world) </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I bow to Lord Vinayaka, the one who brings happiness like the sweet Modaka, the eternal bestower of liberation, adorned with the art and playful as an ornament, the protector of the world. He is the leader of those without a leader, destroyer of the demon-like arrogance, and the remover of inauspiciousness. I offer my salutations to that Vinayaka. (Verse 1) </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> नतेतरातिभीकरं नवोदितार्कभास्वरं<br/> नमत्सुरारिनिर्जरं नताधिकापदुद्धरम् ।<br/> सुरेश्वरं निधीश्वरं गजेश्वरं गणेश्वरं<br/> महेश्वरं तमाश्रये परात्परं निरन्तरम् ॥ २॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> नत - bow, इतरा - other, तिभीकरं - fear-inducing<br/> नव - new, उदित - risen, अर्क - sun, भास्वरं - radiant<br/> नमत - bow, सुर - gods, अरि - enemies, निर्जरं - free from aging<br/> नत - bow, अधिक - beyond, पद - positions, उद्धरं - uplift<br/> सुर - gods, ईश्वरं - Lord, निधी - treasures, ईश्वरं - Lord<br/> गज - elephants, ईश्वरं - Lord, गण - Ganas (attendants), ईश्वरं - Lord<br/> महा - great, ईश्वरं - Lord, तम - that, आश्रये - I take refuge<br/> पर - supreme, आत्परं - beyond, निरन्तरं - eternal (Verse 2) </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I bow to the fear-inducing Lord, who shines like the newly risen sun, I bow to the Lord who frees the gods from aging and uplifts them to higher positions, the Lord of treasures, the Lord of elephants, and the Lord of the Ganas. I take refuge in the great, supreme, eternal Lord. (Verse 2) </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> समस्तलोकशङ्करं निरस्तदैत्यकुञ्जरं<br/> दरेतरोदरं वरं वरेभवक्त्रमक्षरम् ।<br/> कृपाकरं क्षमाकरं मुदाकरं यशस्करं<br/> मनस्करं नमस्कृतां नमस्करोमि भास्वरम् ॥ ३॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> समस्त - all, लोक - worlds, शङ्करं - benefactor<br/> निरस्त - destroyed, दैत्य - demons, कुञ्जरं - elephant<br/> दर - doors, इतर - others, उदरं - stomach<br/> वरं - boon, वर - boons, भव - becoming, क्त्रमक्षरम् - eternal syllable (Om)<br/> कृपा - mercy, करं - doer, क्षमा - forgiveness, करं - doer<br/> मुदा - happiness, करं - doer, यशस्करं - bestower of fame<br/> मनस्करं - bestower of blessings in the mind, नमस्कृतां - saluted<br/> नमस्करोमि - I bow, भास्वरं - radiant (Verse 3) </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I bow to the benefactor of all worlds, the destroyer of demons like elephants, the one with doors in his stomach, the bestower of boons and the eternal syllable (Om). He is the doer of mercy, the doer of forgiveness, the bestower of happiness and fame. I salute the one who blesses us in the mind. I bow to the radiant Lord. (Verse 3) </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> अकिञ्चनार्तिमार्जनं चिरन्तनोक्तिभाजनं<br/> पुरारिपूर्वनन्दनं सुरारिगर्वचर्वणम् ।<br/> प्रपञ्चनाशभीषणं धनञ्जयादिभूषणं<br/> कपोलदानवारणं भजे पुराणवारणम् ॥ ४॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> अकिञ्चन - destitute, आर्ति - suffering, मार्जनं - remover<br/> चिरन्तन - ancient, उक्ति - scriptures, भाजनं - reciter<br/> पुर - city, अरि - enemies, पूर्व - first, नन्दनं - delighter<br/> सुर - gods, अरि - enemies, गर्व - pride, चर्वणं - destroyer<br/> प्रपञ्च - world, नाश - destroyer, भीषणं - fearsome<br/> धन - wealth, जय - conqueror, आदि - and so on, भूषणं - adorned<br/> कपोल - forehead, दान - giver, वारणं - protector<br/> भजे - I worship, पुराण - ancient, वारणं - protector (Verse 4) </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I worship the remover of suffering for the destitute, the reciter of ancient scriptures, the delighter of the city of gods, the destroyer of the pride of enemies. He is the fearsome destroyer of the world, the conqueror of wealth, adorned with various ornaments, the protector of the forehead, and the ancient protector. (Verse 4) </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> नितान्तकान्तदन्तकान्तिमन्तकान्तकात्मजम्<br/> अचिन्त्यरूपमन्तहीनमन्तरायकृन्तनम् ।<br/> हृदन्तरेन्तरं वरं वारिराशिवरेणुजम्<br/> वितानवीतजाननं नमामि तं विनायकम् ॥ ५॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> नितान्त - eternal, कान्त - beauty, दन्त - teeth, कान्ति - shining<br/> मन्त - jewel, कान्त - beauty, कात्मजम् - son (Ganesha)<br/> अचिन्त्य - incomprehensible, रूप - form, मन्त - jewel, हीन - devoid of<br/> मन्त - jewel, अहीन - without, मन्तराय - obstacles, कृन्तनं - destroyer<br/> हृदय - heart, अन्तर - within, अन्तरं - innermost<br/> वरं - boon, वारि - ocean, आशि - seeking, वरेणु - raindrop, जम् - born of<br/> वितान - extensive, वीत - knowledge, जाननं - knower<br/> नमामि - I bow, तं - to Him, विनायकम् - Vinayaka (Verse 5) </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I bow to that eternal beauty, whose shining teeth are like radiant jewels, the beautiful son of Goddess Parvati. His form is incomprehensible and beyond description, the destroyer of obstacles without any obstacles. He resides in the innermost core of the heart. He is the bestower of boons, born from the ocean of the sought-after raindrop of blessings. He has extensive knowledge and is the knower of all. I bow to that Vinayaka. (Verse 5) </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> ॐ सरागिलोकदुर्लभं विरागिलोकपूजितं<br/> सुरासुरैर्नमस्कृतं जरापमृत्युनाशकम् ।<br/> गिरा गुरुं श्रिया हरिं जयन्ति यत्पदार्चकाः<br/> नमामि तं गणाधिपं कृपापयः पयोनिधिम् ॥ १॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'सर'- essence, 'अगिल'- difficult to obtain, लोक- world/region"> सरागिलोकदुर्लभं - Difficult to obtain in this world </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'वि'- without, 'राग'- attachment, 'लोक'- world, 'पूजित'- worshipped"> विरागिलोकपूजितं - Worshipped by those devoid of attachment to the world </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'सुर'- gods, 'असुर'- demons, 'नमस्कृतं'- revered"> सुरासुरैर्नमस्कृतं - Revered by gods and demons </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'जरा'- old age, 'पमृत्यु'- death, 'नाशकं'- destroyer"> जरापमृत्युनाशकम् - Destroyer of old age and death </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'गिरा'- with words, 'गुरुं'- the teacher, 'श्रिया'- with wealth, 'हरिं'- Vishnu"> गिरा गुरुं श्रिया हरिं - I offer my salutations to the teacher, Vishnu, with words and wealth </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'नमामि'- I bow down, 'तं'- to that, 'गणाधिपं'- Lord of all beings, 'कृपापयः'- ocean of mercy, 'पयोनिधिम्'- reservoir of compassion"> नमामि तं गणाधिपं कृपापयः पयोनिधिम् - I bow down to that Lord of all beings, the ocean of mercy and reservoir of compassion </span> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I offer my salutations to the Lord of all beings, Vishnu, who is difficult to obtain in this world, worshipped by those devoid of attachment to the world, revered by gods and demons, the destroyer of old age and death. I bow down to that Lord of all beings, the ocean of mercy and reservoir of compassion. </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> गिरीन्द्रजामुखाम्बुज प्रमोददान भास्करं<br/> करीन्द्रवक्त्रमानताघसङ्घवारणोद्यतम् ।<br/> सरीसृपेश बद्धकुक्षिमाश्रयामि सन्ततं<br/> शरीरकान्ति निर्जिताब्जबन्धुबालसन्ततिम् ॥ २॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'गिरीन्द्र'- Lord of mountains, 'जामुख'- born from Jamadagni's mouth, 'अम्बुज'- lotus, 'प्रमोददान'- source of delight"> गिरीन्द्रजामुखाम्बुज प्रमोददान भास्करं - The sun who is the source of delight like the lotus born from Lord Parashurama's mouth </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'करीन्द्र'- elephant, 'वक्त्र'- face, 'मानता'- revered, 'घसङ्घ'- elephant herd, 'वारण'- protective covering, 'उद्यतं'- risen"> करीन्द्रवक्त्रमानताघसङ्घवारणोद्यतम् - The one with the face like an elephant, revered by the protective covering of elephant herds </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'सरीसृप'- snakes, 'ईश'- Lord, 'बद्ध'- bound, 'कुक्षिम्'- abdomen, 'आश्रयामि'- I take refuge, 'सन्ततं'- forever"> सरीसृपेश बद्धकुक्षिमाश्रयामि सन्ततं - I take refuge in the Lord with snakes as his bound abdomen, forever </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'शरीर'- body, 'कान्ति'- radiance, 'निर्जित'- conquered, 'अब्ज'- lotus, 'बन्धु'- friend, 'बाल'- young"> शरीरकान्ति निर्जिताब्जबन्धुबालसन्ततिम् - The radiance of whose body has conquered the youthfulness of the lotus and a friend of the young </span> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I bow down to the sun, who is the source of delight like the lotus born from Lord Parashurama's mouth, and is revered by the protective covering of elephant herds. I take refuge in the Lord with snakes as his bound abdomen, forever, whose radiance has conquered the youthfulness of the lotus and is a friend of the young. </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> शुकादिमौनिवन्दितं गकारवाच्यमक्षरं<br/> प्रकाममिष्टदायिनं सकामनम्रपङ्क्तये ।<br/> चकासतं चतुर्भुजैः विकासिपद्मपूजितं<br/> प्रकाशितात्मतत्वकं नमाम्यहं गणाधिपम् ॥ ३॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'शुक'- Parrot, 'आदि'- and others, 'मौनि'- sage, 'वन्दितं'- worshipped"> शुकादिमौनिवन्दितं - Worshipped by sages like Shuka and others </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'ग'- the syllable Ga, 'कार'- syllable Ka, 'वाच्यं'- pronounced, 'अक्षरं'- syllable"> गकारवाच्यमक्षरं - The syllable 'Ga' that is pronounced </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'प्र'- fulfilling, 'काम'- desires, 'मिष्ट'- desired, 'दायिनं'- giver"> प्रकाममिष्टदायिनं - The giver of desired objects, fulfilling desires </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'सक'- with, 'काम'- desires, 'नम्र'- humble, 'पङ्क्तये'- line"> सकामनम्रपङ्क्तये - To the line of devotees who approach with desires and humility </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'च'- and, 'कासतं'- shining, 'चतुर्भुजैः'- with four arms, 'विकासि'- expanding, 'पद्म'- lotus, 'पूजितं'- worshipped"> चकासतं चतुर्भुजैः विकासिपद्मपूजितं - The one shining and worshipped with four expanded lotus-like arms </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'प्रकाशित'- manifest, 'आत्मतत्व'- self-knowledge, 'कं'- that, 'नमाम्यहं'- I bow down, 'गणाधिपम्'- Lord of all beings"> प्रकाशितात्मतत्वकं नमाम्यहं गणाधिपम् - I bow down to the Lord of all beings, who manifests self-knowledge </span> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I bow down to the Lord, worshipped by sages like Shuka and others, the syllable 'Ga' that is pronounced, the giver of desired objects, fulfilling desires, to the line of devotees who approach with desires and humility. The one shining and worshipped with four expanded lotus-like arms, I bow down to the Lord of all beings, who manifests self-knowledge. </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> नतेन्द्रियार्थप्रदं नन्दिनन्दनोद्यतं<br/> विभानुकोटिसुन्दरं नन्दनानन्दिनुवंशकम् ।<br/> अवेक्ष्यमूर्तिमानन्दमन्यगोत्रपूजितं<br/> नमामि तं गणाधिपं गजाननं नमामि तं गजाननम् ॥ ४॥ </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'न'- not, 'तेन्द्रिय'- sensory, 'अर्थ'- objects, 'प्रदं'- giver"> नतेन्द्रियार्थप्रदं - The giver of objects not perceivable by the senses </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'नन्दि'- pleasure, 'नन्द'- bliss, 'नोद्यतं'- risen"> नन्दिनन्दनोद्यतं - The one who has risen for the pleasure and bliss of Nandini (Goddess of happiness) </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'विभा'- resplendent, 'नुकोटि'- crore, 'सुन्दरं'- beautiful"> विभानुकोटिसुन्दरं - The one with the beautiful splendor of a crore suns </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'नन्दन'- delight, 'नन्दि'- pleasure, 'नुवंशकं'- descendant"> नन्दनानन्दिनुवंशकम् - The descendant of Nandini who brings delight and pleasure </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'अवेक्ष्य'- beholding, 'मूर्तिमानन्द'- embodiment of bliss, 'अन्य'- other, 'गोत्र'- lineage, 'पूजितं'- worshipped"> अवेक्ष्यमूर्तिमानन्दमन्यगोत्रपूजितं - The one beholding whom brings bliss, worshipped by various lineages </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'नमामि'- I bow down, 'तं'- to that, 'गणाधिपं'- Lord of all beings, 'गजाननं'- elephant-faced, 'नमामि'- I bow down, 'तं'- to that, 'गजाननम्'- elephant-faced"> नमामि तं गणाधिपं गजाननं नमामि तं गजाननम् - I bow down to that Lord of all beings, the elephant-faced one, I bow down to that elephant-faced one </span> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> I bow down to the Lord, the giver of objects not perceivable by the senses, the one who has risen for the pleasure and bliss of Nandini, the one with the beautiful splendor of a crore suns, the descendant of Nandini who brings delight and pleasure, the one beholding whom brings bliss, worshipped by various lineages. I bow down to that Lord of all beings, the elephant-faced one, I bow down to that elephant-faced one. </p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sanskrit-text"/><category term="vedic"/><category term="ganesh"/><category term="sanskrit"/><category term="shlok"/><category term="full-text"/><category term="ganesh"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ganesh pancharatnam]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">सम्पूर्ण चाणक्य नीति</title><link href="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/sampurna-chanakyaniti/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="सम्पूर्ण चाणक्य नीति"/><published>2023-05-26T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-26T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/sampurna-chanakyaniti</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/sampurna-chanakyaniti/"><![CDATA[<p>In development</p> <p>Feel Free to hover over text to understand deeper meaning</p> <div id="chanakya_niti"> <table border="1" class="tg" style="width: 100%"> <colgroup> <col span="1" style="width: 30%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 34%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 36%"/> </colgroup> <thead> <tr> <th class="tg-c3ow">Sanskrit (देवनागरी)</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">शब्दार्थ (Meaning of words)</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">English Translation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> प्रणम्य शिरसा विष्णुं त्रैलोक्याधिपतिं प्रभुम् ।<br/> नानाशास्त्रोद्धृतं वक्ष्ये राजनीतिसमुच्चयम् || </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'प्रणम्य'- pay homage, नम् - to bow, प्र - intensifies the action;"> प्रणम्य-bow with deep respect </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="शिरसा -&gt; शिरस् - head"> शिरसा-head </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="विष् - to pervade/to encompass"> विष्णुं- deity that pervades everywhere </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="त्रै - three,लोक- worlds/realms,अधिपति-supreme ruler"> त्रैलोक्याधिपतिं - ruler of three loka </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline">पश्-to see</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline">अक्ष-eye</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="प्रभु - master"> प्रभुम्-master </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="नानाः - various, शास्त्र - range of subjects/literature/knowledge, उद्धृतं -&gt; उद्-धृ -&gt; uplift">नानाशास्त्रोद्धृतं-uplifter of collection of diverse treatises</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="वच् - to say/to speak">वक्ष्ये-say/discuss</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="राजनीति-strategy/policy of king -&gt; राज - king; नीति -strategy/policy, समुच्चयम् - collection -&gt;सम् -together, उद् - upwards, च - and/to bring forth">राजनीतिसमुच्चयम्-collection of political knowledge </span> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> Bowing with deep respect to the deity Vishnu, the supreme ruler of three realms, I commence by speaking about the comprehensive collection of various political treatises. </p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </div> <p><br/></p> <h4><b></b></h4> <p> </p> <p> </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sanskrit-text"/><category term="vedic"/><category term="sanskrit"/><category term="shlok"/><category term="full-text"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[entire chanakya niti]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">शांति मंत्र</title><link href="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/shantimantra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="शांति मंत्र"/><published>2023-01-02T16:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-02T16:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/shantimantra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2023/shantimantra/"><![CDATA[<p>In development</p> <p>Feel Free to hover over text to understand deeper meaning</p> <div id="bhadram_karnebhihi"> <h5>खालील मंत्रे मुण्डक, मांडूक्य आणि प्रश्न उपनिषदेतून आहेत</h5> <h5> <b>The verses below are from Mundaka, Māndukya and Prashna Upanishad:</b> </h5> <br/> <table border="1" class="tg" style="width: 100%"> <colgroup> <col span="1" style="width: 22%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 38%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 40%"/> </colgroup> <thead> <tr> <th class="tg-c3ow">Sanskrit (देवनागरी)</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">शब्दार्थ (Meaning of words)</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">English Translation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> ॐ भद्रं कर्णेभिः शृणुयाम देवाः ।<br/> भद्रं पश्येमाक्षभिर्यजत्राः ।<br/> स्थिरैरङ्गैस्तुष्टुवाग्‍ँसस्तनूभिः ।<br/> व्यशेम देवहितं यदायुः ।<br/> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="'भद्रयति'-to make happy or prosperous, भद्र - happiness; भद् - to shine"> भद्रं-auspicious </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="कर्ण -&gt; केर् - to cut/to separate, the one that can distinguish different sounds"> कर्ण-ear </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="शृ - syllable relating to acoustics"> शृणोति-to hear </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="देव - in this context giver/helper, in divine enlightenment, Root दिव् - to shine/brighten"> देव-divine/giver </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline">पश्-to see</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline">अक्ष-eye</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="यज् - to sacrifice or to worship, here, it could be the doer/action performer"> यजत्राः-Yajamana </span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="स्थिर -&gt; स्थ -&gt; usually denotes, steadiness/still/stability/strength">स्थिर-stable</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="अङ्ग - division/section or the, whole of something,(can be body or limbs here)">अङ्ग-body</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="तुष्टु - (स्तु+स्तु) - satisfied/contented">तुष्टु-contented</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="वाग्‍ँस -&gt; वाक् - speech/language">वाग्‍ँस-speech organ</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="तनुस्-skin/body/form/stretchable object">तनू-body</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="व्यश-&gt;वस्-to live">व्यश-to live</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="हित-&gt;हि-to obtain (something obtain to benefit),achieved for a purpose">हित-benefit</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="आयु-life/duration/energy/strength,अयति-to move forward in life">आयुः-life/age</span> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> O divine beings, may we hear auspicious words with our ears.<br/> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="Usually yajna performers were the saints/kings, or the doers of the process to whom the salutations were referred to"> May we see the auspicious with our eyes, O performers of the yajña. </span><br/> With <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="Stable limbs/body/posture">stable posture</span> and satisfied mind and body,<br/> May we live a life which is beneficial to the <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="ददाति इति देवः - the givers/providers/divine beings">divine entities</span> </p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> स्वस्ति न इन्द्रो वृद्धश्रवाः।<br/> स्वस्ति नः पूषा विश्ववेदाः।<br/> स्वस्ति नस्तार्क्ष्यो अरिष्टनेमिः।<br/> स्वस्ति नो बृहस्पतिर्दधातु॥<br/> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="स्वस्ति-स्व+अस्ति - the existence of itself, its welfare and good being">स्वस्ति-well-being</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="न-negative">न-Not</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="इन्द्र- often having multiple meanings, 1. derived from इंदु - drop -&gt; deity for rain/lightening, 2. इन्द्रिया - ruler of 5 sense of body">इन्द्र-senses/rain</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="वृद्धश्रवाः-&gt;वृद्ध-old::(वृद्धि-to increase/grow/augment),श्रवा-fame/heared by all (श्रु-to hear)">वृद्धश्रवाः-renowned/famous</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="पूष्-feed/nourish/cherish/prosper, usually annotated to Sun who provides us warmth and nourishment">पूष-feed/nourish</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="विश्व-world(that land spreaded in all direction/that can be encompassed),(विस्-to spread/to enter::व-all direction),वेद-knowledge(विद्-to know) ">विश्ववेदाः-worldly knowledge</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="तार्क्ष्य-&gt;eg.garuda-&gt;तर्क-reasoning,(something continuous process/never fades away), symbol of intelligence;speed;power">तार्क्ष्य-speed/swift entity</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="अरिष्ट(अ+ऋष्टि)-non-righteousness,ऋष्टि(ऋष्-to sprinkle{good fortune})-auspicious,नेमि(to bend), Thus entirely meaning: one who make the evil bend/ward off evil">अरिष्टनेमि-no enemies</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="बृह्-to expand::बृहत्-great/expanded/large,पति-father/leader/master,full meaning:great lord/master/guru:one who knows everything">बृहस्पति-wisdom/guru</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="दा-to give, ददाति-to bestow">दधातु-grant</span> </p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="Literal: May Indra - ruler of rains/senses not harm us,Contextual:May we not be harmed by the nature or be controlled by ours senses">May Indra, the renowned entity, bestow upon us all blessings</span><br/> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="Literal: May Pusha - the feeder/nourisher not deny us from worldly knowledge,Contextual:May we be blessed and nourished by worldy knowledge">May Pusha, the knowledgable, bestow upon us all blessings.</span><br/> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="Literal: May Tarkshya enrich us with profound reasoning but ward off any enemies in the process">May Tarkshya, who is swift as an arrow and has no enemies, bestow upon us all blessings.</span> <span class="tooltip-multiline" data-tooltip="Literal: May Brihaspati not make us devoid of knowledge,Contextual:May we be provided appropriate direction for becoming successful">May Brihaspati, the guru of the divine entities, bestow upon us all blessings.</span> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </div> <p><br/></p> <h4><b>Commentary with respect to current era:</b></h4> <p> For ages, the word देव (deva) has been used to refer to a wide range of entities, such as elders, protectors, worshipped deities, rulers, kings, and more. The verses mentioned above are a form of initial salutations made to these divine entities, with the intention of pleasing them. By serving under such entities, a human life can become more meaningful and fruitful, resulting in benefits for both the individual and the divine. This tradition of offering respect and worship to the divine has been an integral part of Indian culture for thousands of years. </p> <p> Even today, these verses can serve as a form of initial speech used in emails, letters, or text messages to any higher authority for whom we seek a path to success. They can be seen as similar to the acknowledgements and preface that authors provide in their books in the modern context. In ancient times, such acknowledgements were typically found at the beginning of Upanishads or other texts. They served as an expression of respect and gratitude towards the divine entities and higher powers that the authors believed had guided and inspired their work. These salutations were a way of recognizing the importance of the divine in the author's life and work.<br/> By offering these salutations, we can make our path to success easier and smoother. The entities we seek to please could be our parents, bosses, teachers, professors, or anyone who could benefit from our service, and in turn, could help us achieve our goals. These verses have been used since ages towards the elders, protectors, worshipped entities, rulers, kings, etc. and have proven to be effective in pleasing them. Thus, by acknowledging and honoring these entities, we can increase our chances of success and create a positive impact in our lives. </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="upanishad"/><category term="vedic"/><category term="upanishad"/><category term="mantra"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[shanti mantra (before any vedic text)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">365日の紙飛行機</title><link href="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2022/365-days-of-paper-planes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="365日の紙飛行機"/><published>2022-09-18T15:10:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-18T15:10:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2022/365-days-of-paper-planes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mihirrajdixit.github.io/blog/2022/365-days-of-paper-planes/"><![CDATA[<p>Lyricist：(秋元:あきもと)(康:やすし) - Akimoto Yasushi</p> <p><br/></p> <table border="1" class="tg" style="width: 100%"> <colgroup> <col span="1" style="width: 40%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 30%"/> <col span="1" style="width: 30%"/> </colgroup> <thead> <tr> <th class="tg-c3ow">Kanji/Furigana</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">Romaji</th> <th class="tg-c3ow">English</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(朝:あさ)の(空:そら)を(見上:みあ)げて<br/> (今日:きょう)という(一日:いちにち)が<br/> (笑顔:えがお)でいられるように<br/> そっとお(願:ねが)いした</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p class="style37">asa no sora wo miagete<br/> kyou to iu ichinichi ga<br/> egao de irareru you ni<br/> sotto onegai shita</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>Looking up at the morning sky<br/> On this day known as today<br/> I hope I can spend it smiling<br/> I gently wished</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(時:とき)には(雨:あめ)も(降:ふ)って<br/> (涙:なみだ)も(溢:あふ)れるけど<br/> (思:おも)い(通:どお)りにならない(日:ひ)は<br/> (明日:あした) (頑張:がんば)ろう</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>toki ni wa ame mo futte<br/> namida mo afureru kedo<br/> omoidoori ni naranai hi wa<br/> ashita ganbarou</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>Sometimes, rain falls<br/> And tears overflow, but<br/> Days when things don’t go according to plan<br/> Make me want to strive tomorrow</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>ずっと(見:み)てる(夢:ゆめ)は<br/> (私:わたし)がもう(一人:ひとり)いて<br/> やりたいこと (好:す)きなように<br/> (自由:じゆう)にできる(夢:ゆめ)</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>zutto miteru yume wa<br/> watashi ga mou hitori ite<br/> yaritai koto suki na you ni<br/> jiyuu ni dekiru yume</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>The dream I’ve always had<br/> Is to be someone<br/> Who is free to do whatever she wants<br/> That’s my dream</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(人生:じんせい)は(紙:かみ)(飛行機:ひこうき)<br/> (願:ねが)い(乗:の)せて(飛:と)んで(行:い)くよ<br/> (風:かぜ)の(中:なか)を(力:ちから)の(限:かぎ)り<br/> ただ(進:すす)むだけ<br/> その(距離:きょり)を(競:きそ)うより<br/> どう(飛:と)んだか どこを(飛:と)んだのか<br/> それが(一番:いちばん) (大切:たいせつ)なんだ<br/> さあ (心:こころ)のままに<br/> 365(日:にち)</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>jinsei wa kamihikouki<br/> negai nosete tonde yuku yo<br/> kaze no naka wo chikara no kagiri<br/> tada susumu dake<br/> sono kyori wo kisou yori<br/> dou tonda ka doko wo tonda no ka<br/> sore ga ichiban taisetsu nanda<br/> saa kokoro no mama ni<br/> sanbyaku rokujuugo nichi</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>Life is a paper airplane<br/> Flying on with my wishes<br/> With all my might against the wind<br/> Just progressing<br/> Rather than compete for distance<br/> How I flew, where do I fly to<br/> Those are the most important things<br/> Come, like my heart<br/> 365 days</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(星:ほし)はいくつ(見:み)えるか<br/> (何:なに)も(見:み)えない(夜:よる)か<br/> (元気:げんき)が(出:で)ない そんな(時:とき)は<br/> (誰:だれ)かと(話:はな)そう</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>hoshi wa ikutsu mieru ka<br/> nani mo mienai yoru ka<br/> genki ga denai sonna toki wa<br/> dareka to hanasou</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>How many stars can I see?<br/> Or is it a night where nothing can be seen?<br/> When I can’t bring up my energy<br/> I’ll talk to someone</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(人:ひと)は(思:おも)うよりも<br/> (一人:ひとり)ぼっちじゃないんだ<br/> すぐそばのやさしさに<br/> (気:き)づかずにいるだけ</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>hito wa omou yori mo<br/> hitoribocchi ja nainda<br/> sugu soba no yasashisa ni<br/> kidzukazu ni iru dake</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>Humans are not<br/> As alone as they think<br/> Just unable to notice<br/> The kindness right beside them</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(人生:じんせい)は(紙:かみ)(飛行機:ひこうき)<br/> (愛:あい)を(乗:の)せて(飛:と)んでいるよ<br/> (自信持:じしんも)って(広:ひろ)げる(羽根:はね)を<br/> みんなが(見上:みあ)げる<br/> (折:お)り(方:かた)を(知:し)らなくても<br/> いつのまにか(飛:と)ばせるようになる<br/> それが(希望:きぼう) (推進力:すいしんりょく)だ<br/> ああ (楽:たの)しくやろう<br/> 365(日:にち)</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>jinsei wa kamihikouki<br/> ai wo nosete tonde iru yo<br/> jishin motte hirogeru hane wo<br/> minna ga miageru<br/> orikata wo shiranakute mo<br/> itsu no ma ni ka tobaseru you ni naru<br/> sore ga kibou suishinryoku da<br/> aa tanoshiku yarou<br/> sanbyaku rokujuugo nichi</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>Life is a paper airplane<br/> Flying on with love<br/> These wings spread with confidence<br/> Everyone is looking up<br/> Even if you don’t know how to fold one<br/> You’ll be able to fly before you know it<br/> That’s hope, a motivation<br/> Ahh, let’s have fun<br/> 365 days</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(人生:じんせい)は(紙:かみ)(飛行機:ひこうき)<br/> (願:ねが)い(乗:の)せて(飛:と)んで(行:い)くよ<br/> (風:かぜ)の(中:なか)を(力:ちから)の(限:かぎ)り<br/> ただ(進:すす)むだけ<br/> その(距離:きょり)を(競:きそ)うより<br/> どう(飛:と)んだか どこを(飛:と)んだのか<br/> それが(一番:いちばん) (大切:たいせつ)なんだ<br/> さあ (心:こころ)のままに<br/> 365(日:にち)</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>jinsei wa kamihikouki<br/> negai nosete tonde yuku yo<br/> kaze no naka wo chikara no kagiri<br/> tada susumu dake<br/> sono kyori wo kisou yori<br/> dou tonda ka doko wo tonda no ka<br/> sore ga ichiban taisetsu nanda<br/> saa kokoro no mama ni<br/> sanbyaku rokujuugo nichi</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>Life is a paper airplane<br/> Flying on with my wishes<br/> With all my might against the wind<br/> Just progressing<br/> Rather than compete for distance<br/> How I flew, where do I fly to<br/> Those are the most important things<br/> Come, like my heart<br/> 365 days</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>(飛:と)んで(行:い)け!<br/> (飛:と)んでみよう!<br/> (飛:と)んで(行:い)け!<br/> (飛:と)んでみよう!<br/> (飛:と)んで(行:い)け!<br/> (飛:と)んでみよう!</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>tonde yuke!<br/> tonde miyou!<br/> tonde yuke!<br/> tonde miyou!<br/> tonde yuke!<br/> tonde miyou!</p> </td> <td class="tg-c3ow"> <p>Fly on!<br/> Just fly!<br/> Fly on!<br/> Just fly!<br/> Fly on!<br/> Just fly!</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <p>Translation Credits: <a href="http://stage48.net/studio48/365nichinokamihikouki.html">Stage48</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jpop"/><category term="akb48"/><category term="jpop"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[365 Nichi no Kamihikouki / 365 days of paper planes]]></summary></entry></feed>